<!-- retain these comments for translator revision tracking -->
<!-- $Id$ -->

   <sect3 id="netcfg">
   <title>Configuring the Network</title>

<para>

As you enter this step, if the system detects that you have more than
one network device, you'll be asked to choose which device will be
your <emphasis>primary</emphasis> network interface, i.e. the one
which you want to use for installation. The other interfaces won't be
configured at this time. You may configure additional interfaces after
installation is complete; see the <citerefentry>
<refentrytitle>interfaces</refentrytitle> <manvolnum>5</manvolnum>
</citerefentry> man page.

</para>

<sect4 id="netcfg-automatic">
<title>Automatic network configuration</title> 
<para>

By default, &d-i; tries to configure your computer's network
automatically as far as possible.  If the automatic configuration
fails, that may be caused by many factors ranging from an
unplugged network cable to missing infrastructure for automatic
configuration.  For further explanation in case of errors, check
the error messages on the fourth console.  In any case, you will
be asked if you want to retry, or if you want to perform a manual
setup.  Sometimes the network services used for autoconfiguration
can be slow in their responses, so if you are sure everything is
in place, simply start the autoconfiguration attempt again.
If autoconfiguration fails repeatedly, you can instead choose
the manual network setup.

</para>
</sect4>

<sect4 id="netcfg-manual">
<title>Manual network configuration</title>
<para>

The manual network setup in turn asks you a number of questions about
your network, notably
<computeroutput>IP address</computeroutput>,
<computeroutput>Netmask</computeroutput>,
<computeroutput>Gateway</computeroutput>,
<computeroutput>Name server addresses</computeroutput>, and a
<computeroutput>Hostname</computeroutput>.
Moreover, if you have a wireless network interface, you will be asked
to provide your <computeroutput>Wireless ESSID</computeroutput> 
(<quote>wireless network name</quote>) and a <computeroutput>WEP key</computeroutput> or
<computeroutput>WPA/WPA2 passphrase</computeroutput>.
Fill in the answers from
<xref linkend="needed-info"/>.

</para><note><para>

Some technical details you might, or might not, find handy: the program
assumes the network IP address is the bitwise-AND of your system's IP
address and your netmask. The default broadcast address is calculated as
the bitwise OR of your system's IP address with the bitwise negation of
the netmask. It will also guess your gateway.  If you can't find any of
these answers, use the offered defaults &mdash; if necessary, you can
change them by editing <filename>/etc/network/interfaces</filename> once
the system has been installed.

</para></note>
</sect4>

<sect4 id="netcfg-ipv4-ipv6">
<title>IPv4 and IPv6</title>
<para>

From &debian-gnu; 7.0 (<quote>Wheezy</quote>) onwards, &d-i; supports IPv6
as well as the <quote>classic</quote> IPv4. All combinations of IPv4 and
IPv6 (IPv4-only, IPv6-only and dual-stack configurations) are supported.

</para><para>

Autoconfiguration for IPv4 is done via DHCP (Dynamic Host Configuration
Protocol).  Autoconfiguration for IPv6 supports stateless autoconfiguration
using NDP (Neighbor Discovery Protocol, including recursive DNS server
(RDNSS) assignment), stateful autoconfiguration via DHCPv6 and mixed
stateless/stateful autoconfiguration (address configuration via NDP,
additional parameters via DHCPv6).

</para>
</sect4>

   </sect3>
