<!-- retain these comments for translator revision tracking -->
<!-- $Id: initialize-partition.xml,v 1.2 2003/09/19 02:01:40 toff Exp $ -->


 <sect1 id="init-partition">
 <title>``Initialize a Linux Partition''</title>
<para>

At this point, the next menu item presented should be ``Initialize a
Linux Partition''.  If it isn't, it is because you haven't completed
the disk partitioning process, or you haven't made one of the menu
choices dealing with your swap partition.

</para><para>

You can initialize a Linux partition, or alternately you can mount a
previously-initialized one.  Note that
<command>debian-installer</command> will <emphasis>not</emphasis>
upgrade an old system without destroying it.  If you're upgrading,
Debian can usually upgrade itself using 
<command>apt-get dist-upgrade</command>, and you won't need to use
<command>debian-installer</command>.

</para><para>

Thus, if you are using old disk partitions that are not empty, i.e.,
if you want to just throw away what is on them, you should initialize
them (which erases all files).  Moreover, you must initialize any
partitions that you created in the disk partitioning step.  About the
only reason to mount a partition without initializing it at this point
would be to mount a partition upon which you have already performed
some part of the installation process using this same set of
installation floppies.

</para><para>

Select ``Initialize a Linux Partition'' to initialize and mount the
<filename>/</filename> disk partition. The first partition that you
mount or initialize will be the one mounted as <filename>/</filename>
(pronounced ``root'').

</para><para>

You will be asked about whether to scan for bad blocks.  The default
here is to skip the bad block scan, since the scan can be time
consuming, and modern disk drive controllers internally detect and
deal with bad blocks.  However, if you are at all unsure about the
quality of your disk drive, or if you have a rather old system, you
should probably do the bad block scan.

</para><para>

The next prompts are just confirmation steps.  You will be asked to
confirm your action, since initializing is destructive to any data on
the partition, and you will be informed that the partition is being
mounted as <filename>/</filename>, the root partition.

<footnote><para>

Technically, it's being mounted at <filename>/target</filename>; when
you reboot into the system itself, that will become
<filename>/</filename>.

</para></footnote>

</para><para>

Once you've mounted the <filename>/</filename> partition, if you have
additional file systems that you wish to initialize and mount, you
should use the ``Alternate'' menu item.  This is for those who have
created separate partitions for 
<![ %not-powerpc; [<filename>/boot</filename>]]>, 
<filename>/var</filename>,
<filename>/usr</filename> or others, which ought to be initialized and
mounted at this time.

</para>
 </sect1>

