<!-- retain these comments for translator revision tracking -->
<!-- $Id: administrivia.xml -->

<chapter id="administrivia">
 <title>Administrivia</title>


 <sect1 id="about">
 <title>About This Document</title>

<para>
This document is written in DocBook XML.
Output formats are generated by programs from the
<classname>docbook-xml</classname> package.</para>

<para>In order to increase the maintainability of this document, we use a
number of SGML features, such as entities and marked sections.  These
play a role akin to variables and conditionals in programming
languages.  The SGML source to this document contains information for
each different architecture &mdash; marked sections are used to isolate
certain bits of text as architecture-specific.</para>


 </sect1>


 <sect1 id="contributing">
 <title>Contributing to This Document</title>

<para>If you have problems or suggestions regarding this document, you
should probably submit them as a bug report against the package
<classname>installer</classname>.  See the <classname>reportbug</classname> package 
or read the online documentation
of the <ulink url="http://bugs.debian.org/">Debian Bug Tracking System</ulink>.
It would be nice if you could check the 
<ulink url="http://bugs.debian.org/installer">open bugs against install-doc</ulink>
to see whether your problem has already been reported. If so, you can supply additional corroboration or
helpful information to <email><replaceable>XXXX</replaceable>
@bugs.debian.org</email>, where<replaceable>XXXX</replaceable> 
is the number for the already-reported bug.
</para>

<para>Better yet, get a copy of the DocBook source for this document, and
produce patches against it.  The DocBook source can be found at the
<ulink url="http://cvs.debian.org/debian-installer/doc/manual/">debian-installer CVSWeb</ulink>. If you're not familiar with DocBook, don't worry:
there is a simple cheatsheet in the manuals directory that will get
you started. It's like html, but oriented towards the meaning of 
the text rather than the presentation. Patches submitted to the 
debian-boot mailing list (see below) are welcomed.
For instructions on how to check out the sources via CVS, see
<ulink url="http://cvs.debian.org/cgi-bin/viewcvs.cgi/~checkout~/debian-installer/README?tag=HEAD%26content-type=text/plain">README</ulink>
from the source root directory.
</para>

<para>Please do <emphasis>not</emphasis> contact the authors of this
document directly.  There is also a discussion list for
<classname>debian-installer</classname>, which includes discussions of
this manual.  The mailing list is
<email>debian-boot@lists.debian.org</email>.  Instructions for
subscribing to this list can be found at the 
<ulink url="http://www.debian.org/MailingLists/subscribe">
Debian Mailing List Subscription</ulink> page; or you can 
browse the 
<ulink url="http://lists.debian.org/">Debian Mailing List Archives</ulink>
online.
</para> 

 </sect1> 


 <sect1 id="contributors">
 <title>Major Contributions</title> 

<para>Many, many Debian users and
developers contributed to this document.  Particular note must be made
for Michael Schmitz (m68k support), Frank Neumann (original author of
the <ulink url="http://www.informatik.uni-oldenburg.de/~amigo/debian_inst.html"></ulink>), Arto Astala, Eric
Delaunay/Ben Collins (SPARC information), Tapio Lehtonen, and Stéphane
Bortzmeyer for numerous edits and text.</para> <para>Extremely helpful
text and information was found in Jim Mintha's HOWTO for network
booting (no URL available), the <ulink url="http://www.debian.org/doc/FAQ/"></ulink>, the <ulink url="http://www.linux-m68k.org/faq/faq.html"></ulink>,
the <ulink url="http://www.ultralinux.org/faq.html">Linux for
SPARC Processors FAQ</ulink>, the 
<ulink url="http://linux.iol.unh.edu/linux/alpha/faq/">Linux/Alpha
FAQ></ulink>, 
amongst others.  The maintainers of these freely available and
rich sources of information must be recognized.
</para> 
 </sect1> 

 <sect1 id="trademarks"> <title>Trademark Acknowledgement</title>
<para>
All trademarks are property of their respective trademark
owners.
</para>
 </sect1> 
</chapter>
